While rumors and reports continue to
swirl about a possible deal with Iran,
the clock is still ticking for an
economy that is way too close to the
point of no return. In fact, for Europe,
there is the non-trivial chance it may
have already gone past it because the
data we have so far for May just got
absolutely slammed. So, this is all in
the context of a European economy that
looks like it may have already found the
cliff with S&P Global describing the
situation in France as, quote, dire.
In fact, the only factor holding
everything up is an emergency stock
building free-for-all that is, again,
going back to S&P, already fizzling out.
That means payback. Some of the figures
that we're seeing are at three-year
lows. Several big ones are at five-year
lows. Worst estimates since 2020. And
these are some of the most critical
pieces. And remember, Europe is the
place to watch as a leading global
indicator. Yet, despite what the data is
saying, the ECB continues to charge
headlong toward a rate hike. Maybe the
Trump administration can save the
European central bankers from tricheing
themselves too while they're at it. Keep
in mind, though, the increasingly nasty
economic trajectory isn't just for
Europe to sort out. Walmart, in its
earnings report which came out this past
week, had some very sharp warnings about
US consumers, including how much
gasoline is now seeing Americans buying.
And the retailer also had an update on
how much tax refund money they have
left. So, while we all wait for the next
update from Washington, the clock
continues to really tick down on the
energy shock.
The worse the economy gets in Europe,
the more certain European central
bankers are that they need to hike rates
to combat inflation that's already being
taken care of by the weak economy. Some
things just never change, right, Steve?
We've seen this movie before. Sharp
drop-off in the economy, which is
consistent with energy prices going up
because, let's face it, the economy was
in bad shape to begin with. We've been
talking about this the entire time. Bad
shape to begin with in a fragile state.
You raise energy prices, which you can't
get away from, and you have to you've
got to pay for it someplace else. So,
you've got a weak economy, energy shock,
demand falls off, and now the data is
picking up on that demand falling off,
and the media is running around this
shocked as hell, whereas central bankers
are saying, "What weakness? We're more
concerned about inflation."
>> You know, Jeff, this was probably one of
the most interesting PMIs I've seen in a
very, very long time because you know,
we can go back and you all remember when
it was the services sector was booming,
the manufacturing sector was weak, and
everybody said, "The services sector is
going to pull the global economy out of
the slump. Manufacturing doesn't matter
anymore. It's not important." And all of
a sudden, you get this big, steep
decline in services. And so, now you're
talking about the energy shock. This is
the, you know, the real-world data
saying, "Yes, this is a problem because
consumers are now cutting back on
services." So, this is a very clear
evidence. But on the manufacturing side,
you get a little opposite. You say,
"Well, wait a minute, it's booming." But
as you said, "We're just building stock.
We're building up inventory because we
think prices are going even higher, and
we already know demand is dropping." And
so, this is interesting because you've
got services dropping. The question now
isn't when the manufacturers start
curtailing, it's what is the
second-order effect. It's going to hit
the labor market in such a big way
because they're going to have to lay
people off. And so, all of a sudden, you
start looking at stagflation and energy
shocks. You get rising prices, which we
have. You get weakening demand, which we
can now clearly see in the services
sector. And then the last piece is the
labor market. And now we're seeing signs
that that's coming and soon. And yet,
again, like you said, the response,
"Well, we've got to hike rates."
>> Yeah, so I mean, the by the numbers
here, S&P Global's Eurozone composite
fell to 47 and 1/2 for the month of
April or for the month of May, excuse
me, which was a 31-month low because
services absolutely crashed to 46.4,
down another 1.2 points on the month, a
63-month
low. So, as Steve said, services are
being hammered by consumers who can no
longer afford higher gasoline costs
along I mean, look, the labor market's
weak. You're not seeing income growth
nearly enough to begin with, let alone
to be able to absorb another hit from
energy costs. And businesses, for the
same same thing, especially smaller and
medium-sized businesses, they've already
been stung repeatedly over the last
couple years. Last year in particular,
they to the point where they already
stopped hiring just like the US
counterparts. So, you raise energy
costs, which again, you cannot get away
from, what are they going to do? They're
going to cut costs everywhere else. And
S&P, they had some bad news where it
came to employment. Uh they said,
"Although modest, the fifth successive
monthly fall in employment was the most
pronounced since November 2020." I love
how they call it modest, but, you know,
it's modest at the beginning. It's what
comes after modest that we're really
worried about. So, November 2020 low in
employment. And it said, "In fact,
excluding the COVID-19 pandemic, the
reduction in workforce numbers was the
largest since August of 2013."
And August of 2013 was when Europe was
just coming out of the 2011-2012
re-recession. So, already, I mean, this
is just May. We're not even 3 months
into this thing, and we're already
getting pretty solid signs of the
historic energy shock case, which is I
mean, this plays out time and time again
the same way because you have the same
ingredients. You've got a fragile, not
resilient economy, not an economy that
was in a good place. You've got a
fragile economy that gets hit with a
shock that it just cannot absorb, and
the immediate reactions to it should not
be, "Oh my god, inflation's coming."
>> What is a Euro Dollar University
membership? It's where understanding the
monetary world isn't a mystery, it's a
method. If you're serious about your
financial education, and you want
clarity in a world of volatility and
misunderstanding,
this is for you.
Mainstream education has left so many
gaps on the most foundational concepts,
making sense of everything is
practically impossible otherwise. With
our memberships, we'll fill in
everything that you've been missing.
Whether you're starting out or
sharpening your edge, our memberships
scale with your goals. At Euro Dollar
University, we teach you about how money
really works so that you can evaluate
fundamentals and make grounded
decisions. With a Euro Dollar University
membership, you get a comprehensive
library of foundational and advanced
lectures, in-depth case studies, and
real-world analyses, live Q&A sessions,
regular updates on macro trends, and
even some central bank policies. And
most important, how to interpret
critical derivative market signals you
will not find anywhere else.
You can't be in a position to succeed if
you don't know how it all really works
and fits together. So, if you're ready
to explore master monetary systems both
past and future with structure, clarity,
and confidence. Click the link in the
description to visit
eurodollar.university/memberships
to join us today.
>> Yeah, Jeff. And and then you get the
reaction of central bankers who are just
it's like tunnel vision on inflation
right now. And and then idea and and
again let let let's pretend for a moment
that you know monetary policy works.
Okay, so in you know inflation's rising,
you want to raise interest rates to
curtail demand. But, it's not a demand
issue. This isn't demand-led inflation.
And that's what
>> it's like how are they going to get more
oil out of the Persian Gulf, right? It's
like how are you going to fix that
problem?
>> Yeah. So, it's like you want to curtail
demand at a point where prices are
rising and demand is falling. If
anything, you want to be cutting rates.
You're again under the notion that maybe
cutting rates would stoke demand and
make it easier. But, nevertheless, you
you talk about policy mistakes. I know
we're coming up on July 2026. That's the
there's June 2026. That's the next
meeting for the ECB. And this kind of
reminds me of July I'm saying July of
2008 when they hiked rates because
they're worried about inflation and then
the global financial crisis hit right
after that. And and you start to think,
well, you know,
there's that saying, you know, you do
things rhyme? Well, not exactly, but
gosh, you you almost feel the policy
mistake coming at the worst possible
time.
>> Yeah, I think the the assumption was
that the Europe and particularly kept
saying it's a good place, it's a good
place. They thought maybe the economy is
a bit more resilient and therefore they
could focus on demand. So, energy costs
go up, what they're worried about is
that those costs spill over into what
they call second and third order
effects, which is, you know, gasoline
prices go up and that leads to higher
costs for shipping other stuff around
the world. So, other goods prices have
to go up in response and because the
economy was resilient, at least they
assumed it was, that would mean those
those prices would be passed along to
other to consumers in other prices. And
then you all of a sudden you've got this
inflation everybody, you know, is afraid
of. However, what are rate what are rate
hikes going to do about that? Let's
assuming rate hikes actually did work,
what they're really saying is, okay,
energy costs are going to go up, we have
to pay for energy. We're going to
restrain the rest of the economy that's
already getting weaker because of energy
prices and we need to hold the rest of
the economy back just so that we don't
have an inflationary breakout. So, even
if you believe rate hikes work, the
theory still doesn't make any sense.
We've got to make a bad situation worse
by hiking rates. Now, I know it's
essential bankers say that we have to do
this. This is not our fault. We've got
to raise rates because that's, you know,
this is how we believe things work. But
that's it's just the whole thing just
completely falls apart and it is
completely falling apart in the European
economy right now. I mean, France, I
know you know the Steve France, the the
PMI for France was the composite there
43 and a half, which is a five-year low.
Even Germany's, which ticked up a little
bit, it only did so because of another
little temporary boost in uh in
And as the S&P guy said for France, I'm
going to read the quote here. "This
shock has materially lifted recession
risk for the Eurozone's second largest
economy." Describing the numbers as
\quote} "dire." The concern is that a
broader uplift in the economy's overall
price level raises the further raises
the risk of further demand destruction.
It doesn't raise the risk, we're already
seeing evidence that's already taking
place. And that's a symptom of the
fragility. The fact that we just went I
mean
whenever a shock shows up, there's
always an ability of any economic system
to absorb that shock in the short run,
right?
Uh employers don't immediately start
firing workers when gasoline hits, you
know, three, four dollars a gallon. They
say, "Okay, we'll sit here, we'll take
the short run hit because we don't want
to get rid of our workers. Getting rid
of workers is bad. It means we got to
bring them back if we're wrong and we
got to retrain them. There's all sorts
of costs, there's productivity that gets
sacrificed. So, you don't want to react
immediately. And so, usually when a
shock happens, it takes a couple months
for that shock to really produce some of
the most severe results because there's
a shock absorption capacity there. We're
only a couple months into this and we're
already seeing these numbers turn really
negative and we're getting you know,
sentiment. They're talking about the
United States and consumers. University
of Michigan. The the consumer index fell
sharply there. Another indication in the
US, Walmart. Walmart in their earnings
this past week said and they gave us one
key number, one key number that I think
most people missed, which was um the
average amount of gasoline that their
customers are buying from the Walmart
stores fell below 10 gallons for the
first time since 2022, which simply
means consumers are pulling back.
They're only buying what they what they
can. So, we're seeing these these demand
destruction signals more clearly in
Europe, but they're there in an
increasing number of ways all over the
place.
>> And you know, what's interesting about
this, Jeff? I've I've kind of been
asking just out loud of when do you hit
that tipping point cuz we know when an
energy shock hits, as you said, there's
a shock absorber that can buffer it. And
it depends on, you know, what point is
past the point of no return because if
the economy strong, it can it can absorb
it for a while. And as we look, you
know, really focus on Europe, we can see
France is saying, "Well, well, we're
already past that point." Germany is
saying, "Well, as soon as we're done,
you know, building stock in our
manufacturing sector, well, we don't
have really anything left to stand on."
So, you look at you look at Europe and
if those two economies go, again,
they're the biggest two in the Eurozone,
well, the rest of them stand no chance.
So, it looks like Europe is right on,
you know, crossing that point of no
return. Now, we're not here at that
point in the US yet, but based on what
you're saying with Walmart saying is
low-income consumers are taking a hit,
high-income consumers are spending more,
which is equally a red flag when when
wealthy people start shopping at
Walmart. And again, staggering that
they're probably going to the store,
buying what they can, saying, "Gosh, I
need some gas and oh, I only have this
much left. Well, that's what I'm going
to buy," which is, you know, just a few
gallons. So, you start to think of are
we there yet? No, but we're not far
behind. So, as we look at Europe and we
what we see here is, "Hey, what's
happening there is soon to happen here."
>> Yeah, that's the point. That's why we're
focusing on Europe because Europe is
sort of an early warning indicator. The
Europeans, first of all, weaker much
weaker shape than the US. Forget that,
you know, what Lagarde said, "A good
place." I mean, she kept saying that
over and over again and everybody at the
ECB all last fall, "Oh, Europe's a good
place. Europe's a good place." Almost as
if they keep repeating the phrase it
would actually happen. Sort of like it's
a voodoo spell or something like that.
But Europe was in much worse shape than
anywhere else. Plus, they're more
susceptible to the supply shock that's
taking place now than say the US is. The
US is more insulated on the energy side.
So, Europe has two reasons to watch them
as sort of an early warning signal about
where this energy shock is going and and
how soon that tipping point might
actually show up. Steve, you're exactly
right. That's what we're really
interested in.
If the longer this goes, and I think
everybody agrees with it, even central
bankers would agree with this. The
longer this goes, the more you're the
more likely you're going to hit that
tipping point. Now, they think because
the economy was at least they used to
think because they thought the economy
was resilient that tipping point was
much further into the future and
therefore they had much more runway to,
you know, focus on inflation and try to
pretend that they're Paul Volcker
reincarnated. So, instead, what we're
getting is more and more evidence that
they were wrong about the resiliency,
which means the tipping point has moved
much closer to today, if not, you know,
France, which may have already passed
that. So, if France has already passed
the tipping point, we start to see more
and more confirmation that's the case
and you see Germany has gone past the
tipping point and other places like
Australia. Australia, where the Reserve
Bank of Australia has hiked rates three
times this year thinking the economy was
resilient, that inflation was the bigger
risk. Well, the Australians just
reported some pretty sobering and pretty
declining labor market numbers.
Unemployment unexpectedly rose and jobs
unexpectedly fell in April. And now the
Reserve Bank of Australia is saying,
"Uh-oh, maybe we need to pause our rate
hikes because they're already getting to
the point where they're realizing uh
maybe that was a policy error." So, I
mean, Australia is not in danger of
falling off. Australia, the miracle
economy that, you know, does well in
every recessionary period, but it
suggests that the weakness is severe
enough that even Australia, which is
supposed to be heavily resilient, might
be already falling off. And if
Australian if Australia's Central Bank
is thinking, "Oh, we made a mistake on
rate hikes," that's something got to pay
attention to, especially in the context
of the early warnings that we're getting
out of Europe.
>> Yeah, and one of the challenges, Jeff,
is I I think people look at the US stock
market, which, you know, right back to
all-time highs going, you know, or very
close to that going into the holiday
weekend.
>> does not care about anything, right?
Stock Stock market says, "Hey, is
everybody buying? I'm going to buy,
too."
>> Right. So, you So, people are looking at
that and saying, "Well, we must be
immune to it." And And the reality is
we're not. We're still seeing early
signs of that. And the key now is if we
look at Europe and say, "Okay, that's a
proxy of what we're about to see," It's
really about watching the services
sector. Now, here's something
interesting. You know, we we've talked
about the kind of the Disney World PMI.
Now,
this is interesting cuz we got both
water parks open again. They're They
have not been that busy, but here's
what's notable. I was reading an article
this morning that said over the summer,
which is usually our peak season here,
that all the data suggests that ride
lines, which is a good a proxy of
demand, are going to be like 30% lower.
In some cases, there could be weeks
worse 50% lower because of projected
demand is dropping off that
significantly. Uh for the Orlando area,
that's massive because summer here, you
you don't even want to go to the parks.
There's so many people. But, if that is
indeed true, then what we're seeing in
Europe's services sector is coming here.
It's going to hit in another month or
so, and that means when we look for our
manufacturing sector, what do we see in
our own PMIs? The exact, you know,
virtually the same language. Well,
manufacturing's booming and hiring
because they're building stock. Why?
Because nobody thinks energy prices are
coming down this point, and that's fair.
So, nevertheless, what happens again
once they built up all this inventory
and front run it just like they did the
pandemic, just like they did the
tariffs, just like they're doing now.
What happens to labor market? Well, we
know what's going to happen. It's going
to be a lot of workers on the
unemployment line.
>> Yeah, that's where all of this ends up.
I mean, that's that's why energy shocks
always are not always, but you know,
substantial energy shocks and recessions
go hand in hand. It's because you have a
fragile economy that's usually these
shocks show up on the downswing in the
cycle where it's already late stage
stuff to begin with. Employers are
already getting pessimistic. They're
already saying, you know, business isn't
as good as I thought it was. And then
along comes, you know, energy prices
just soar ahead, and they're like, okay,
uh we'll give it a couple months, but if
things don't turn around, we got to
start cutting people. We got to start
cutting back on investments. We got to
cut We got to save cash. We got to do
all sorts of defensive types of
activities and behavior, which lead to
the inevitable recession, the cliff.
And the point we're making here with
with Europe um
services is the big one because when
you're forced to spend more on
discretionary items, and again, Walmart
even said on discretionary, uh they're
not even spending what they used to
because they can't afford it. So, if
you're at the if you're already maxed
out on gasoline, and that's the United
States, it's worse in Europe because you
gasoline and energy is so much more
expensive over there. If you're already
maxed out, you got to cut back someplace
else because again, jobs are
disappearing. It's not like you can go
out and get a better paying job
overnight that that that makes up the
cost in the gasoline or anything else
that's going to go up beside it. So,
you've got to start cutting back and the
thing that you're going to cut back on
first is what's easiest to cut that you
don't really need. You're going to cut
back on some subscriptions, you're going
to cut back on services, you're going to
cut back on your vacations. You wanted
to go somewhere this summer, you're not
going to be able to. You're going to
have to stay local. You're going to have
to really cut back and scrimp. Um and
we're already getting all the signs of
that. Uh consumer pessimism isn't
consumer pessimism about nothing. It's
always been tied to jobs and incomes and
perceptions of both. And also tied in
with price changes because consumers
know price changes are over and above
what they can afford to begin with. And
with no avenue to fix that in the job
market, they're they're feeling stuck.
That's why they're so pessimistic
because they know we're going to get
hammered again and there is absolutely
nothing we can do about it except go
even further into that same recession
direction. So, we're watching Europe
because because Europe is the I hate to
use the term canary in a coal mine cuz
that's a it's overused, but essentially,
like you said, Steve, it's the proxy for
the early warning signals that suggest
if there is a cliff here, if we're past
the tipping point, that's where we're
going to see it, European services.
>> Yeah, absolutely, Jeff, because it's not
about what people say. Yes, people are
pessimistic. It's about what they do.
And Walmart's saying, "Hey, they're
cutting back their discretionary.
They're worried about their staples.
They're not buying as much gas." We just
heard from Home Depot and Lowe's this
week, and you and I both covered those,
and they said, "Guys, sales were
negative in May, but in April they went
negative."
It's like, "Okay, those are signs
again." You You just start looking
around and saying, "Okay, is what's
happening in Europe likely to happen
here?" And again, we're seeing all these
little signs, and yes, as they add up,
it gets worse. And you think about
what's really been pushing our economy,
you know, to keep us out of the same
business in Europe, it's the tax checks,
which is again that those refund checks.
And the other question I keep asking is,
"When do they run out?" And the answer
is starting to be is, "Oh, it looks like
they were starting to run out somewhere
around April." So, that's a good
indication of, you know, okay, if that's
the case, then over the next couple of
months, they should be completely gone,
and then that's where we really see the
reality of the pessimism in the surveys,
like from University of Michigan, really
start to match what we see in the
spending habits in the retail sales
space.
>> Yeah, and that's the other thing Walmart
said, there's two big things. I mean,
the biggest thing to me was the
gasoline, but the other thing that the
CFO said, Mr. Rainey, was that yes,
we're seeing consumers run out of their
their tax refund checks. So, if Walmart
is saying we're already seeing that in
our stores, we can detect it by I mean,
look, they've got so much information at
their fingertips, real-time information.
And because Walmart is so huge and their
reach is so far and so far-reaching,
they can look at the data and say, "We
know to to the penny what everybody's
doing." Uh so, for for them to raise
those two points, gasoline, not buying
you know, less than $10 or less than 10
gallon average in gasoline, and we're
also detecting that the consumers are
running out of their tax refunds here in
the United States, those are a couple of
US-specific warning signs that go along
with the what we're hearing and seeing
out of Europe that suggest, "Okay, if if
Europe's reaching the tipping point, we
may not actually be all that far
behind." Which also explains why some of
the behavior we're getting in certain
markets, like
front end of the yield curve has been
doing funky stuff, things that people
would not imagine given the situation
where everybody believes central bankers
are going to hike rates because central
bankers to a man basically have said
we're going to hike rates. I mean, even
Christopher Waller, the ultra dove, came
out and said
"Yeah, we're as likely to hike rates as
we are to cut rates." Which is a big
thing because he's the one that's always
been arguing for rate cuts. But the
markets
yes, the two-year Treasury yield is
going up, which is the market saying
there's a good chance these these people
are going to treachery themselves and
hike rates in the middle of a downturn.
But short-term rates like term SOFR and
Treasury bill rates, they're actually
declining right now, which is the market
hedging and saying
they may not get the chance. They all
want to hike rates, but we're seeing
things deteriorate significantly and
quickly enough that we're going to bet
we're going to make some substantial
bets to the point that term SOFR is
really falling off that we're going to
make some substantial bets they don't
even get to hike rates because we're
seeing the classic energy shock case.
And that is to borrow the S&P guys'
phrase, it really is a dire situation.